这幅摄影出自济斯瓦夫·贝克辛斯基之手
This is a photograph by Zdzisław Beksiński.
在他长达半个世纪的艺术生涯中
Over the course of a 50-year career in art,
他将梦境与魇祷具象于画布和胶片
he would materialize dreams and nightmares onto canvas and celluloid,
为波兰艺术博得了世界性的关注，并助力定义了现代重金属美学
bring a global eye to Polish art, and would help to define modern heavy metal aesthetic.
他于1929年降生，其故乡萨诺克
Born in 1929, his birthplace, Sanok,
在二战前夕，曾是波兰犹太人口最稠密的地区之一
had one of the largest populations of Jewish people in all of Poland
城中近三成居民皆为犹太裔
in the lead-up to World War II, roughly 30% of the city.
到了1940年
And in 1940,
一座集中营就在城郊拔地而起，并在接下来的三年里持续运转
the Zdzisław concentration camp was created just on the outskirts, and would remain functional for the next three years.
战争的余烬之中
In the aftermath of the war,
当他的祖国为苏联所占领，贝克辛斯基开始用镜头记录他周遭的世界
Beksiński would begin to photograph the world that he saw around him during the Soviet occupation of his country.
毋庸置疑，他整个青少年时期所亲历的恐怖
And it is undeniable that the horrors he experienced through his entire adolescence
都深刻地烙印在他日后的创作心境之中
would later play a massive role in the mindset of his works that he would go on to create.
尽管未曾接受过正规的艺术训练
Although not formally trained in art,
他还是在1955年修习了建筑学
in 1955, he would study architecture,
并由此掌握了对他日后助益良多的绘图技巧
and develop drafting skills through that that would later help him in more than one way.
因为这不仅锻炼了他的手绘能力，更让他得以了解建筑的历史与象征意义
Because as well as training his hand, he would also learn the history and symbolism of architecture
从而能通过画作发表社会评论
that would allow him to make social commentary through his paintings.
学成之后，他重返故乡萨诺克
After finishing his education, he would return home to Sanok,
在一家名为Autosan的建筑公司设计巴士
and would design buses for a construction company called Autosan.
但在此期间，他仍不断地深入探索摄影
But during this time, he would continue to experiment more with his photography,
将工地上寻得的物件融入自己的照片创作中
incorporating objects that he found at the construction site into the pictures that he took,
并决定将摄影作为自己职业外的副业
and decided as a side project to his career that he would become a part-time photographer.
正是在1957年
And it was here, in 1957,
贝克辛斯基凭借其最早的摄影作品，骤然间撼动了整个艺术界
that Beksiński immediately disrupted the art world with his earliest works of photography.
当时摄影界背后的哲学理念，是所谓的直接摄影或纯粹摄影
The philosophical idea behind photography at the time was that of straight photography, or pure photography,
其代表人物有保罗·斯特兰德，爱德华·韦斯顿和安塞尔·亚当斯等艺术家
and the likes of artists such as Paul Strand, Edward Weston, and Ansel Adams,
这种流派的理念在于，摄影师需运用相机，将被摄对象拍得尽可能清晰锐利
in which the objective of the photographer was to use the camera to create as sharpened images possible of the subject,
并借助光影来展现其每一寸天然的纹理
using light to demonstrate every natural texture available.
这种风格诞生于对画意摄影的扬弃
This style was born out of a rejection of pictorialism,
后者是二十世纪初叶主流的艺术摄影风格
which was the reigning style of art photography in the early 1900s,
画意摄影师试图以一种朦胧而模糊的方式捕捉生活
wherein the photographer would try to capture life in a hazy, obscure way,
近乎于印象派画家的笔触
similar to that of the Impressionist painters.
纯粹摄影则反对此道
Pure photography stood against this staged
它抗拒画意派在作品中营造的那种刻意安排的，虚假的生活观念
false idea of life that the pictorialists created within their work,
并力求呈现事物本来的面貌，而非浪漫主义者眼中的模样
and tried to present objects as they truly were, rather than how a romantic would see them.
因此，当贝克辛斯基在1957年公布其摄影作品《施虐者的束衣》时
And so when Beksiński unveiled his photograph, Sadist's Corset, in 1957,
作品中那种风格化的，精心安排的姿态，立即引发了强烈的抵制
there was an immediate backlash to its stylized, posed nature
因为它颠覆了传统的裸体摄影
that rejected the traditional nude,
画面中的人像背对镜头，头部与腿部被裁切，姿态僵硬，毫无情色意味
facing the figure away from the camera, cropping out the head and legs in a very non-sexual, rigid, standing position.
摄影评论家阿尔弗雷德·卢戈基公开批评了这幅照片，他宣称
Photography critic Alfred Ligocki publicly criticized the photograph, saying that
超现实主义摄影不应得到承认
Surrealist photography should not be acknowledged,
因为它代表了摄影师对被摄对象的直接干预
because of its direct interference with the photographed subject on the part of the photographer,
未能如实地展现拍摄对象本来的样子
that it didn't properly represent the subject as it really was,
并声称贝克辛斯基的作品是反摄影的
claiming that Beksiński's work was anti-photography.
贝克辛斯基随后在《摄影》杂志上公开发文回应，题为
Beksiński then responded to this publicly in Photography Magazine, with an article titled
《摄影的危机与克服之道》
The Crisis of Photography and the Perspective to Overcome It,
他指出，当时大行其道的纯粹摄影风格，未能给艺术表达留下空间
saying that the pervasive style of pure photography didn't allow for artistic expression,
而这种媒介理应赋予艺术家进行艺术创作的自由，只要艺术家有此意愿
and that the medium should grant that to an artist to make an artistic statement, if the artist wants to do that.
而这种哲学理念，你可以在他所有的早期摄影作品中窥见一斑
And this philosophy is something that you can see in all of his early photographic works.
照片中的主体无一不经过精心操控和设计，以非常特定的方式摆出姿势
The subjects are all manipulated, directed, and posed in very specific ways,
并总是以某种方式被遮蔽
and were always obscured in some fashion.
在《施虐者的束衣》中，前景里一把失焦的椅子将主体分割成了碎片
An out-of-focus chair in the foreground segments the subject of Seda's corset into pieces.
在这里，镜子打破了身体的自然对称
Here, mirrors disrupt the natural symmetry of the body,
主体被裁剪，被拍成剪影，或被刻意处理成失焦状态
subjects are cropped, photographed as silhouettes, purposefully shown out of focus,
而阴影则使面容变得暧昧不清，令人困惑
and shadows make faces ambiguous and confusing to look at.
到了1960年代初
By the time of the early 1960s,
尽管他已是声名鹊起的摄影师
even though he was a renowned photographer,
却毅然决然地放弃了这一媒介
he quit working within the medium entirely
并将自己所有的摄影作品捐赠给了萨诺克的历史博物馆
and donated all of his photographs to the Historical Museum in Sonak,
他声称通过这种艺术形式，他已再无新意可言
stating that he had nothing else to say through that art form,
摄影限制了他的想象力
and that it limited his imagination.
尽管今天的贝克辛斯基完全是以其画作闻名
And even though Beksiński today is known entirely for his paintings,
但在他1950年代的摄影作品中
you can see here in his photographic works of the 1950s
你已经可以看见他后来标志性的存在主义风格之滥觞
the formation of what would go on to be his trademark existential style.
从1960年代初到1980年代中期
From the beginning of the 1960s to the mid-1980s,
Beksiński would enter the era of his career that he would become most known for with the Fantastic series.
贝克辛斯基以其“奇幻系列”步入了他最为人所熟知的创作时期
该系列将建筑，灵性
Which melded architecture, spiritualism,
情色，战争与梦境逻辑融为一体，描绘出一幅幅地狱图景
eroticism, war, and dream logic into a series of hellscape paintings.
贝克辛斯基创作的所有艺术作品均无标题
Every work of art created by Bekshinsky was untitled.
他不喜欢为艺术命名的概念，因为这可能会在艺术家与观众之间
He didn't like the concept of titling art because of the possibility of creating a misconstrued meaning
造成意义的误解或先入为主的阐释
or perceived interpretation of the work from the artist to the audience.
他在2002年的一次采访中解释道，在他看来，诠释是他人强加的
He explained in a 2002 interview that in his opinion, interpretation is imposed by others.
恕我直言，绘画是用来欣赏或沉思的
Speaking immodestly, paintings are to be admired or contemplated.
欣赏它，而无需追问其意
Admired without asking what it means.
倘若我有什么想说的，我会写下来或说出来
If I had something to say, I would write it down or say it.
我无需借助绘画来表达
I don't need painting for that.
事实上，他根本不喜欢解读作品这个概念
In fact, he didn't really like the concept of interpreting the work at all.
并希望画作仅仅作为画作本身而存在
And wanted the paintings to just stand on their own as paintings.
他甚至会因评论家试图为他的作品寻找简单答案而感到不快
And would even get upset with critics who tried to come up with a simple answer for what his work meant.
他还曾说过，意义于我而言毫无意义
Saying also at one point that meaning is meaningless to me.
我不在乎象征手法
I do not care for symbolism.
我画我所画，从不为某个故事而冥思苦想
And I paint what I paint without meditating on a story.
所以我在此也不打算这么做
So I'm not going to try and do that here.
也不会就他全部作品的整体意义提出什么宏大的论点
And offer up some grand thesis of what his body of work means as a whole.
我想他或许是对的，他的作品是如此多元
I think he is probably correct in saying that his work is so diverse.
并且每一幅画都太过复杂
And that each individual painting is too complex.
非我或其他任何人所能轻易概括
For me or anyone else to do that well.
但尽管他有此意愿，我仍要冒昧地说，他的许多作品中存在着共通之处
But despite his wishes, I will go so far as to say that there are common similarities in many works from him.
这使我在欣赏他这一时期的画作时
That make it difficult for me to not think of his life.
很难不联想到他的生平和他成长的政治气候
And the political climate that he grew up in when viewing his paintings from this time.
这一系列几乎每一幅作品都感觉像他在直面一些非常私人的事物
Almost every single one of this set feels like him confronting something very personal
那些他年少时必定目睹或经历过的一切
that he must have seen or experienced in his youth.
同时他也在探索那些显然曾深深吸引并萦绕于他心头的观念
As he also explores concepts that obviously captivated and haunted him.
因此在这里，我想花些时间来探讨我眼中他作品里最常见的主题
And so here I would like to take some time to discuss what I see as the most common themes within his work.
他在二战中成长的经历显然对他影响至深
His experiences growing up in World War II obviously affected him deeply.
也是我能从他画作中看到的最通常的主题
And is the most reoccurring topic that I see in his paintings.
此作，一个丑陋的红色生物将自己隐藏在典雅的古希腊罗马建筑之后
Here an ugly red creature conceals itself behind the facade of elegant Greco-Roman architecture.
战争头盔是一个不断重现的意象
War helmets are a constant reoccurring image,
比如这里，一些人骑着头盔，身后拖着一具尸体
such as here where individuals ride one, dragging a body behind them.
燃烧的建筑，毁灭与混乱主宰着他的世界
Burning buildings, destruction, and chaos reigns in his worlds.
而我认为蓝色在这些场景中意义非凡
And I think the color blue is significant in these scenes.
你可能不知道
If you aren't aware,
普鲁士蓝这种颜色，得名于生产这种颜料时所用的普鲁士酸
the color Prussian blue is named after the Prussic acid that is used to produce that color in paint.
普鲁士酸又被称为氢氰酸
Prussic acid is also known as hydrogen cyanide.
虽然是用一种氰化物制成的，如今的颜料本身并无毒性
And while the paint itself today is not toxic despite being created with a form of cyanide.
但由它制成的其他产品，例如德国人在二战期间
Other products made from it, such as the pesticide Zyklon B,
毒气室中使用的杀虫剂齐克隆B，却是剧毒无比
that would be used by the Germans in gas chambers during World War II, are extremely deadly.
众所周知，在特定条件下，根据铁含量和酸碱度以及湿度的不同
And are known under certain circumstances depending on iron and pH levels, as well as humidity,
在频繁接触该物质的物体表面
to leave a blue residue on surfaces
会留下一层蓝色残留物
that are in frequent contact with the substance,
其化学成分与那种颜料完全相同
that is chemically identical to that paint.
有两幅画，我尤其相信贝克辛斯基是在指涉这一点
There are two paintings, in particular, that I believe Beksiński is referencing this in.
其一，一个酷似死亡化身的身影，笼罩在普鲁士蓝之中
Here, where a figure reminiscent of common depictions of death, shrouded in Prussian blue,
注视着一列满载宗教符号的囚车，车上拥挤不堪的枯瘦人影被运往远方
watches as a train of carts covered in religious symbols carries emaciated figures away, who are packed together tightly.
其二，或许是同一个身影，盘旋在摇篮中的婴儿之上
As well as here, where possibly the same figure hovers over a child in a cradle,
而他身后一个男人正被群鸟活生生地吞食
while a man is eaten alive by birds behind him.
墙上刻着一行字，“in hoc signo vinces”
The words, in hoc signo vinces, is carved into the wall.
这是一句拉丁短语，意为
A Latin phrase meaning,
“凭此信徽，汝可得胜”
In this sign, thou shalt conquer.
此外，我认为还有一点值得注意
It is also relevant, I think, to note,
这句短语曾是美国纳粹党常用的一个流行口号
that this phrase was a common popular slogan used by the American Nazi Party.
人体几乎是贝克辛斯基所有作品的主题
The human body is the subject of almost every Beksiński work.
和他作品中的大多数主题一样
And like most themes within his work,
它们往往融合成一个共同的虚无主义核心
they tend to blend together into one common core of nihilism.
在我看来，他对消瘦躯体的描绘与战争紧密相连
His portrayal of thin bodies is very much, in my mind, tied to the war.
这些躯体也常常与宗教符号一同出现
And they are also often presented with religious symbols,
而宗教符号本身又总是与毁灭相伴，并最终回溯至战争
which themselves are also always shown with destruction tying back into war,
形成一种相互冲突的观念之间不断的循环碰撞
in a constant recycling collision of conflicting ideas.
他一生画了数百幅图像
He painted hundreds of images in his life,
对我而言，每一幅都是一个宏大的霍布斯式人性宣言中的微小碎片
and to me they are each individually small pieces of a larger single Hobbesian statement on human nature.
贝克辛斯基画中的身体从不寻常，它们几乎总是与其他事物交融
The bodies of Beksiński's paintings are never normal, and are almost always blending into something else,
不断延展和扭曲着原有的形态
stretching and obscuring the original form.
许多身体共同构成一个新的生物
Many bodies form a new creature.
面孔绽放成自然之景
Faces bloom into nature.
建筑由身体构筑而成
Buildings are constructed out of bodies.
巴黎圣母院竟是血肉之躯
Notre Dame is made of flesh.
数字被纹上或刻入人们的肌肤
Numbers are tattooed or carved into people.
一个人变成了建筑，一个躯干变成了椅子
A man turns into a building, and a torso into a chair.
最后这几幅，或许是对
With these last few possibly being a critique,
德国人将受害者制成肥皂或灯罩等家居用品的暴行的一种批判
of the victims of the Germans being turned into household objects, such as soap or lampshades.
他描绘的每一个人都是对生命的戏仿
Each person depicted is a parody of life,
唯一的共同点是他们总是异常消瘦
with the only common element being that they are always thinner than they should be.
一具尸骸在演奏小提琴
A corpse plays the violin.
一个残破的舞者摆着姿势
A ruined dancer poses.
面孔变幻不定，时而这样，时而那样，以至于可以说它们已不再是面孔
The faces shift, this way and that way, until the argument could be made that they are no longer faces at all.
它们通常被裁剪或分割成块
They are usually cropped or segmented into pieces,
以近乎自然的方式摆放，却又在某种程度上显得全然不自然
positioned in almost natural ways, and yet somehow entirely unnatural at the same time.
这些身体的布局也与人群的意象相关
And the positioning of the bodies also ties into the idea of crowds,
他们围绕着超凡的政府官员和宗教人物
surrounding larger-than-life government officials and religious figures as well.
群体心理在他的作品中受到了尖锐的批判
As the idea of crowd mentality is critiqued heavily in his work,
置身于庞大群体中的人，或茫然地凝视前方，或在狂喜的愤怒中咬牙切齿
where those in large groups stare vacantly forward or gnash their teeth in joyous anger.
此处，一大群人，或许代表着死亡，头戴钢盔，阻断了前行的道路
Here, a large group, probably representing death, wearing helmets block the way forward on a path.
这里，一颗巨大的头颅正在吞噬大众
And here, a great head devours the masses.
而在宗教方面，一个巨大的存在盘旋在地球上空，其前袋中装着宗教的符号
And on the religious side, a massive being hovers over the earth, with the symbol of religion in its front pocket.
一位红衣主教的面容病态而腐烂
A cardinal appears with a diseased, rotting face.
巴黎圣母院的庭院里坟墓遍地
Graves litter the yard of Notre Dame.
无数的十字架从战争的废墟中升起
And many, many crosses rise up out of the destruction of war.
但同样也有许多画作，其背后并没有如此昭然若揭的可能含义
But there are just as many paintings that don't have as overt of a possible meaning behind them.
这正是我说难以将他的所有作品归结为一个确定论题的原因
Which is why I say that it's difficult to lump all of his output into one definite thesis.
正如难以用一个简洁的句子来概括一个人完整的一生
Just in the same way that it would be difficult to place the entirety of a man's life into one neat sentence.
生命是纷繁复杂的，仅仅因为他年轻时目睹了践踏人权的恐怖
Life is messy, and just because he witnessed the horrors of human rights violations as a youth,
并不意味着这就构成了他作为一个人的全部
doesn't mean that makes up everything about him as a person.
还有许多像这样的画作，对我而言充满了神秘的嗡鸣
And there are many paintings like these that hum with mystery to me.
而这也是我最欣赏他的一点
And that is one of the things that I appreciate most about him.
就是当你以为你几乎要将他作为一名艺术家完全看透时
Is that you can think you almost have him pinned down as an artist.
你又会发现，比如，他曾创作过一组施虐倾向的情色素描
And then you'll discover, for instance, that he created a set of sadistic, erotic drawings
这会让你大吃一惊，因为它们与他创作过的任何其他作品都截然不同
that surprises you because they are totally unlike anything else that he ever worked on.
1990年代是我个人最不喜欢的贝克辛斯基艺术时期
The 1990s are personally my least favorite era of Beksiński's art.
但我并不因此责怪他
But I don't blame him for this.
和当时许多有创造力的人一样
As with many creative people at the time,
他也迷上了数字艺术带来的新可能性
he became enamored with the new possibilities that digital art offered.
他曾一度重拾摄影
And for a while, he returned to photography,
使用像Photoshop这样的新软件来处理自己的照片
using new programs such as Photoshop to manipulate his photographs,
以及他人拍摄的照片，从而创造出新的图像
as well as those taken by others, to create new images out of them.
他当时曾说
He said in this time that,
这项工作让我的思维焕然一新
there is a certain refreshment of mind in this work,
视角与绘画时完全不同
the view from a totally different perspective than at painting.
通过玩转这些程序，我能以任何角度创造出人造的现实
Playing with these programs, I can create artificial reality at any angle
并以具象的方式将其拍摄下来，那便是创作的最终成果
and figuratively photograph it, which would be the final result of creation.
但在我看来，他这一时期所创造的这些人造现实
But the artificial reality of these works that he created in this time,
与他之前的作品相比，水平不可同日而语
to me, are not on the same level as what would have come before, in my opinion.
它们无疑出自同一个头脑和同一个视角
They definitely come from the same mind and the same perspective.
但这些作品给我的感觉不那么原始，不那么发自肺腑或充满情感
But these feel less raw to me, less visceral or emotional.
他重新拾起了“奇幻时期”的早期风格
I enjoy him revisiting imagery from earlier in his career,
并创作了这幅数字版的巴黎圣母院
that he developed during the Fantastic Period,
这一点让我很欣赏
such as doing this digital work of Notre Dame.
但我确实觉得许多美术家以及漫画家
But I do feel like a lot of fine artists, as well as comic artists,
在那个时代都因为在新技术尚未成熟时就试图拥抱它们而受到了束缚
were held back in this era by trying to embrace new technologies before they were perfected.
我想贝克辛斯基最终也意识到了这一点
And I think that Beksiński realized this as well eventually,
因为他对数字艺术感到失望
as he became frustrated with digital art,
并在21世纪初放弃了它，重归绘画
and abandoned it by the 2000s and would return to painting.
但不幸的是，这并没有持续太久
But unfortunately, this would not last for long,
2005年2月21日
as on the 21st of February, 2005,
他与一个名叫罗伯特的男子发生争执
he entered an argument with a man named Robert,
此人是他管家的儿子
the son of his housekeeper,
他想借大约相当于一百美元的钱
who wanted to borrow the equivalent of about $100.
贝克辛斯基拒绝了
Vekshinsky refused,
争吵开始激烈
the argument became heated,
两人继而发生肢体冲突
and the two entered into an altercation,
罗伯特刺了贝克辛斯基十七刀
and Robert stabbed Beksiński 17 times,
杀害了他
killing him.
这不仅夺去了他的生命
Robbing him not only of his life,
也让这个世界失去了更多贝克辛斯基的画作
but the world also of more Beksiński paintings.
那一年，火人节为了纪念他，展示了一个T字形的红色十字架
That year Burning Man would display a red cross in the shape of a T in his honor.
不久之后，萨诺克市
And soon after, the city of Sanok
在一座当地的城堡里开设了一家专门展示他作品的博物馆
would open a museum dedicated to his work in a local castle
至今仍在开放
that is still open to this day.
贝克辛斯基无疑是现代波兰艺术诞生的象征
Beksiński is undeniably the symbol of the birth of modern Polish art,
但我也相信，他象征着一种回应
but I also believe that he stands as a symbol of a reaction
对世界历史上一个极为混乱的特定时期的回应
to a very specific chaotic time in world history,
这是一个亲历者的视角，他目睹了这一切可怕的发生和展开
from a perspective that lived through it and saw it unfold as it all horribly happened.
历经战争，历经灾难
Through war, through travesty,
历经占领与极权主义
through occupation and totalitarianism,
他将这些尽收眼底，铭记于心
he took these things in and held onto them,
直到我认为它们最终迸发成一种纯粹的
before I think they exploded into a pure,
对于生命之恐怖的，感性的，发自肺腑的回应
emotional, visceral reaction at the horrors of life.
而这种艺术视角
And the artistic vantage point
为我们提供了关于那个时代的情感信息
that provides emotional information about this time
是无价之宝
is invaluable.